Guide to the Allan Gurganus Papers, 1961-2019 RL.11748
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Personal Papers, 1917-2018; undated
  - Family Papers, 1942-2003; undated
    - Bill Draper article, undated (Box 46)
    - Gurganus genealogy, undated (Box 46)
    - Kinston Camporee map, 1965 (Box 46)
    - Gurganus Bros. Supermarket article, undated (Box 46)
    - The Brothers Gurganus gallery exhibit, undated (Box 46)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 46)
    - Bruce Gurganus's letter to the editor, undated (Box 46)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Morris article, undated (Box 46)
    - Beauty Queen article, with a note to Ethel Gurganus, undated (Box 46)
  - Family Documents, 1937-1989; undated
    This subseries includes Gurganus family artifacts, and is arranged chronologically.
    - Ethel Gurganus's Bible, undated (Box 47)
    - Marvin Gurganus's Rocky Mount High School diploma, 1937 (Box 67)
    - Allan Gurganus's baby book, 1947 (Box 47)
    - Christian youth workbook, 1963 (Box 47)
    - Allan Gurganus Boy Scout yearbook, 1963-1964 (Box 47)
    - Marvin Gurganus's passport, 1970 (Box 47)
    - Ethel Gurganus's passport, 1970 (Box 47)
    - Ethel Gurganus's nametag, undated (Box 47)
    - Ethel Gurganus's 50th high school reunion, 1985 (Box 47)
    - Allan Gurganus's Kings Point nametage and article, 1989 (Box 47)
    - Rocky Mount High School yearbook, 1964 (Box 48)
    - Allan Gurganus's North Carolina sketches, undated (Box 48)
  - Early Life and Career, 1955-2013; undated
    This subseries includes documents from Gurganus's life before he began writing, and is arranged chronologically where possible.
    - Documents from early life, 1955-1970; undated; 13 folders (Box 49)
      Includes early school assignments; yearbooks; certificates; copies of the Rocky Mount Senior High School publication, The Paradigm; and high school graduation announcement.
    - Art exhibition articles, 1962-1972; undated (Box 49)
      Includes newspaper accounts of Gurganus's art exhibitions.
    - Newspaper articles, 1959-1964; 4 folders (Box 49)
      Includes newspaper articles written by Gurganus about the Fannie Gorsham School; and Rocky Mount Senior High School, The Blackbird.
    - Newspaper articles, 1975-1991; undated (Box 49)
      Includes newspaper articles about Gurganus's grants; reviews; and writing.
    - PEN/Faulkner nominees article, 1992 (Box 49)
    - Skidmore College honorary doctor of letters, 2009 (Box 49)
    - Naval career, 1965-1969; 2013; undated; 8 folders (Box 49)
      Includes documents related to Gurganus's naval service on the USS Yorktown, including Selective Service System card; newspaper articles; Yorktown newsletter; and illustrations.
    - US Naval Training Center, 1967 (Box 22)
    - US Navy Silver Anniversary, 1993 (Box 22)
  - Events, 1958-2010; undated
    This subseries is arranged chronologically where dates are available.
    - Event documents, 1958-2010; undated; 26 folders (Box 53)
      Includes invitations; playbills; and programs from events attended by, and of interest to Gurganus. Events include a Christmas Musical Festival; a North Carolina artists' exhibition; an Ambassador Book award; a Bessie Schonberg Tribute; a hot dog gay dance; and an Iowa Writers' Workshop paper.
    - Event flier, An Ode to Artifice, undated (Box 67)
      Includes Gurganus illustration for his drawing exhibit.
    - Exhibit photographs, Allan Gurganus: A Writer's Sketchbook, Power Plant Gallery, Durham, North Carolina, 2019-01 (Digital-materials SET-0002)
      Eighteen photographs by Hoang Nguyen, of Allan Gurganus's drawings and paintings exhibited at the Power Plant Gallery in Durham, North Carolina.
    - A Celebration of Award-Winning Writer Allan Gurganus, 2019-01-17
      Video and audio of a reception for and reading by Allan Gurganus, celebrating the acquisition of his papers by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
      - Transfer of papers (Digital-materials SET-0001, Video-file OnTransferofPapers.mp4)
      - Allan Gurganus reading - video (Digital-materials SET-0001, Video-file AllanGurganusReadingJan17_FullVideo.mp4)
      - Allan Gurganus reading - audio (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file AllanGurganusReadingJan17_2019.wav)
  - Interviews and Biographies, 1982-2018; undated
    This subseries contains interviews with, and biographies about Gurganus, and is arranged chronologically where dates are available.
    - Interviews and biographies, 1988-1994; 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Interviews and biographies, 1982-2003; 3 folders (Box 67)
      Includes oversized clippings.
    - When I'm Fog on a Coffin Lid, 1993 (Box 53)
      Includes an interview published in the Southern Review.
    - Interviews and biographies, 1995-2002; 4 folders (Box 53)
      Includes an interview published in Mirabella magazine.
    - Interviews and biographies, 2010-2018; undated; 8 folders (Box 54)
      Includes an article in RL Magazine on Allan Gurganus Papers.
    - North Carolina Literary Review, 2018 (Box 22)
      Includes an interview with Gurganus.
    - Videos from the Road, undated (Box 71, Video-cassette RL11748-VHS-0005)
      Includes collaborations with Ellen Spiro.
    - Macneil/Lehrer Report, 1990 Sep 1 (Box 71, Video-cassette RL11748-VHS-0006)
      Includes a Gurganus interview.
    - Walt Whitman, undated (Box 72, Dvd RL11748-DVD-0022)
      Gurganus is included.
    - Pass It On...A Portrait of the Teaching Career of Reynolds Price, 2009 (Box 72, Dvd RL11748-DVD-0023)
  - Private Papers, 1839-2018; undated
    This subseries includes materials Gurganus kept in his home, and is arranged in alphabetical groups.
    - Appointment books and journals, 1978-1980; 1988; 1995; 1997-1998; 6 items (Box 55)
    - Appointment books and journals, 2001-2006; 6 items (Box 56)
    - Appointment books and journals, 2007-2014; 7 items (Box 57)
      Includes notebook with drafts of The Erotic History of a Southern Baptist Church.
    - Appointment books and journals, 2015-2018; 4 items (Box 58)
    - Artifacts, 1960; 1989; 1991-1992; 1996; 2004; undated; 8 folders (Box 54)
      Includes a gay car air freshener; drawings by Muhammad Ali's cornerman, Fernando "Ferdie" Pacheco; and a 1992 Democratic National Convention press pass.
    - Artifacts, Clan Fraser of Lovat, 1960 (Box 22)
      Fraser, Charles Ian
    - Artifacts, oversized, undated; 2 folders (Box 60)
      Includes Cub Scouts faux skin with patches for Rocky Mount Pack 31, Den 4; and History is Lunch... t-shirt for The Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All.
    - Artifacts, vintage, 1839-1889; 1904; -1930; 1953-1971; 1991; 12 folders (Box 54)
      Includes signed James Howie cartes des visite; Lectures on English literature; Evening Party Amusements; Poetical Selections; YMCA ribbon; collected postcards including Alice the Alligator Girl; signed Over the Top with the Motor Transport Corps YMCA program; Porgy and Bess program; and Edgemont Presbyterian Church plans.
    - Letters, personal ads, 1987; 1990; 2 folders (Box 54)
      Includes personal ads placed by Gurganus, and letters written to him in response.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1947-2007; undated; 39 folders (Box 66)
      Includes oversized clippings and copies of newspaper articles, including: Punch & Judy show banned as sadism; RMSHS theater productions; Vivian Smith McMillan; Gurganus Dansforth finalist; Manly Wade Wellman; Karl Wagner; A Vanishing South?; Jesse Helms articles; Joanne Meschery; Where the beat meet the elite; From Hamburger Hill to Bull Run; Teletubbies say eh-oh; Vollis Simpson; Alan Shapiro; Doug Marlette; nude images; a third grade class article; and articles regarding Gurganus.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1962; 1975; 1994; 3 folders (Box 67)
      Includes clippings and copies of newspaper articles including The Art Student; John F. Kennedy photographs in The Globe; Barbara Feldon visiting the USS Yorktown; and Confederate widows get Army benefits.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1988-1997; 2000; 2013; undated (Box 54)
      Includes clippings and copies of newspaper articles of local interest, and with unusual titles, including Man asks for dog's company in court; Rabid raccoon attacks cow's head; Gay men beware; and RMSH gains thirteen teachers.
    - Notes, 1984; 1996; undated (Box 59)
      Includes old address book.
    - Notes, Allan Gurganus, 1997; 2002; undated (Box 59)
      Includes handwritten notes; writing fragments; and original faxes.
    - Notes, Allan Gurganus, 1997; undated (Box 59)
      Includes typed notes; writing fragments; and Allan Gurganus's List of Favorite Books for Summer.
    - Notes, and drawings from Easter Island, undated (Box 59)
    - Notes, from friends, undated (Box 59)
    - Notes, Allan Gurganus, 1995 (Box 67)
      Includes a doodle of a penis on a photograph in The New York Times Magazine.
    - Notes, untitled or undated, 1968; 1991; 1999; 6 folders (Box 59)
      Includes notes, articles, photocopies.
    - Mooney-Surprise Attack on Harper's Ferry, undated (Box 72, Cd RL11748-CD-0001)
      Includes a copy of the Mooney painting.
    - A Call to Renewal, Songs of Separation, of Rest and Resolution: A Recital in the Time of AIDS, 1993 Sep 17 (Box 72, Audio-cassette RL11748-CS-0005)
      Includes Gurganus reading.
    - Town Meeting on Books, undated (Box 72, Audio-cassette RL11748-CS-0007)
    - Flood tapes, 1999 Dec; undated; 4 items (Box 72, Audio-cassette RL11748-MCS-0001 - RL11748-MCS-0004)
      Includes Flood tapes, Tarboro, Bob Barnhill and Betsy Squires; Vivian; master; and Weeks house.
  - Friends, 1976-2018; undated (Box 59)
    This subseries reflects Gurganus's ongoing friendships. Memorials and obituaries are also included as Gurganus has lost friends to AIDS, or the natural aging process. Also included are articles and speeches.
    - Cuthrell, Hiram Johnson, Jr., 1991 (Box 59)
      Includes memorial by Gurganus.
    - Eatman, George, undated (Box 59)
    - Evans, David Bruce, 1998 (Box 59)
    - Harnack, Curtis, 2013 (Box 59)
    - Linney, Romulus, 2011 (Box 59)
    - Margolies, Malka, 1997 (Box 59)
    - Matheson, Elizabeth, undated (Box 59)
    - McElwee, Ross, 1995 (Box 59)
      Includes a proposal for the documentary Tobacco Road.
    - Merrill, James, 1977-1995; 12 folders (Box 61)
      Includes photocopies of correspondence between Gurguanus and Merrill, and Peter Hooten; published poetry; Rhapsody on Czech Themes, for Allan Gurganus, published in Yale Review; a eulogy written by Gurganus; a playbill for Phaedra; a proposal and script for Voices from Sandover; a prospectus for Last Poems; and correspondence with Merrill's estate.
    - Millard, Charles, 1992-2018; undated; 14 folders (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence between Gurganus and Charles Millard. Also includes Millard's correspondence with George Nick; Michael Trapp; Nicholas McGegan; and Elizabeth Matheson. Gurganus's eulogy for Millard is also included.
    - Nagano, Paul, 1976; 1978 (Box 59)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1993-1999 (Box 67)
      Includes clippings related to Doug Marlette, Ellen Spiro, and Bruce Weber.
    - Riner, Ed, undated (Box 59)
    - Sapp, Daniel, 1998 (Box 59)
    - Sapp, Daniel, 1998 (Box 67)
      Includes Sapp's obituary.
    - Simpson, Mona, 1990 (Box 59)
    - Toler, Charlotte Wilkinson, 1995 (Box 59)
    - Vereano, David, undated (Box 59)
  - Financial, Legal, 1975-2005; undated
    Collection contains potentially sensitive information. Contact Research Services for Access.
    This subseries includes financial and legal records related to Gurganus's writing, and legal affairs, and is arranged chronologically.
    - Edward Thayer Draper-Savage will, 1975 (Box 64)
    - Payments and royalties, 1990-2005 (Box 64)
      Includes royalty payments for The Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All, and The Practical Heart.
    - Writing agreements, 1990; 2005 (Box 64)
      Includes agreements with Random House; American Scholar; and Algonquin Books.
    - Arts Council gift, 1991 (Box 64)
    - Spada vs. Eatman, legal documents, 1991-1992; 2 folders (Box 64)
    - Ethel Gurganus trust, legal documents, 1996-1997 (Box 64)
    - Expenses, 1996; 1999; undated (Box 64)
    - Duke Special Collections, 1997 (Box 64)
  - Academics, Gurganus as Student, 1968-2011; undated
    This subseries includes materials from Gurganus's time as a student at Sarah Lawrence College.
    - Applications, reports, 1968-1975 (Box 63)
      Includes Gurganus's reports from Sarah Lawrence College; teaching assistantship application; application for graduate Writers' Workshop at University of Iowa; and letter reporting passage of Master of Fine Arts examination.
    - Sarah Lawrence Alumni Magazine, 1973 (Box 63)
    - Sarah Lawrence College, course evaluations, 1979 (Box 63)
    - Sarah Lawrence College correspondence, 1983-2011; undated (Box 63)
    - Sarah Lawrence magazine, 1990 (Box 63)
  - Academics, Gurganus as Teacher, 1980-2010; undated
    In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
    This subseries includes Gurganus's work as a teacher at Sarah Lawrence College; and the Iowa Writers' Workshop.
    - Sarah Lawrence College, faculty report on students, 1980 (Box 63)
      FERPA information restricted until 2055.
    - Sarah Lawrence College, administrative correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 63)
    - Grace Paley Scholarship Fund, 1990; 2000 (Box 63)
    - Student letters, 2002 (Box 63)
    - Writers' Workshop evaluations, 2010 (Box 63)
    - Reading samples, undated (Box 63)
    - Teaching notes, undated (Box 63)
  - Photographs, 1953-2017; undated
    This subseries includes family and professional photographs of Gurganus, and is arranged chronologically where dates are available.
    - Gurganus family, 1953-1965; undated (Box 65)
      Includes wedding; infant; and childhood photographs, as well as Scottish ancestors.
    - Gurganus family, oversized, 1966 (Box 67)
    - Portraits, Allan Gurganus, 1963-1975 (Box 65)
    - Portrait, Allan Gurganus, oversized, 1990 (Box 67)
    - Portraits, Allan Gurganus, 1989-1994 (Box 65)
    - Art, undated (Box 65)
      Includes Gurganus's paintings; and drawings of leather men by Etienne aka Dom Orejudos.
    - Gurganus, home, 1988; undated (Box 65)
      Includes Gurganus's home and garden.
    - Gurganus, home, oversized, undated (Box 67)
    - Individuals, 1986-1988; undated (Box 65)
      Includes photographs of Heather Lewis, Tim Miller, and unidentified individuals.
    - Groups, 1983-1998; undated (Box 65)
      Includes photographs of Gurganus and friends; unidentified groups; and John Irving and family.
    - Events, 1989; 1992; 2014-2017; undated (Box 65)
      Includes photographs of Gurganus at readings, and other unidentified events.
    - Teaching at Club Boulevard Elementary School, 2000 Mar 19 (Box 65)
    - Confederate Widow Tells All, undated (Box 65)
      Includes photographs of Gurganus in costume on film set of a television mini-series.
- Artwork, 1963-2018; undated
  This Series includes Gurganus's doodles, drawings, paintings, and sketches, and are arranged by materials and approximate date of creation. Instances included may be related to Gurganus titles. The early work dates from first grade, then progresses through grade school and senior high school. Sketchbooks and loose drawings reflect Gurganus's use of pencil; pen and ink; watercolors; and collage through 2018. Many of the works are undated.
  - Sketchbooks - pencil; pen and ink; watercolor, 1963-1965; undated; 7 items (Box 50)
    Sketchbooks may include loose sketches and drawings.
  - Sketchbooks - pencil; pen and ink; watercolor, 1966-1972; undated; 8 items (Box 51)
  - Sketchbooks - pencil; pen and ink; watercolor, 1968; 1984; undated; 6 items (Box 68)
  - Drawings - pen and ink; watercolor; colored pencil, undated; 12 items (Box 52)
  - Drawings - watercolor; pen and ink, 1964; undated; 2 items (Box 52)
    Includes Angels No. 2; and City Study.
  - Drawings - book illustrations, undated; 13 items (Box 52)
    Includes sheet music for Blessed Assurance.
  - Sketches, and titled, undated; 9 items (Box 52)
    Includes American Condiments Aspiring to the Condition of a Morandi; Fresh Air, Moderate Breeze; Madame Bovary Steps Out!; American Icon: "I Pledge Allegiance..."; sketches; and wings sketches.
  - Pen and ink; watercolor; block print, undated; 17 items (Box 52)
  - Sketches, and titled, 2004; undated; 7 items (Box 52)
    Includes Lehman Brady Lecture illustrations; My Credentials, Sir; Pittsburgh Pirates; Mother and sons, Fairview Road, 1946-1986; Vision in Copenhagen; Belated valentine's greetings; and illustrations, home.
  - Drawings - charcoal, undated; 2 items (Box 52)
  - Titled; pen and ink, 1970; undated; 8 items (Box 52)
    Includes Woman Bearing the Weight of Her Whimsy; Minstrels All; and Pope Becoming Object.
  - Block print on handmade paper, undated; 5 items (Box 52)
  - Collage, Music, 1964 (Box 52)
  - Early work - watercolor; charcoal, 1967; undated; 4 items (Box 52)
    Includes Gurganus's eighth grade work.
  - Early work - pencil; pen and ink, 1971; undated; 6 items (Box 52)
    Includes 2 Cows + 2 Goats.
  - Early work - watercolor; pen and ink, 1964; undated; 10 items (Box 52)
    Includes Sax; If and When; and Bar.
  - Early work - first grade, undated (Box 69)
  - Early work - pencil; pen and ink, undated; 20 items (Box 69)
  - Early work - paintings, undated; 11 items (Box 69)
  - Line drawing prints, undated; 4 items (Box 69)
    Includes a Rembrandt reproduction.
  - Pen and ink, and titled, undated; 16 items (Box 69)
    Includes art from Blessed Assurance; and History is Lunch.
  - Sketches and fragments, and titled - pen and ink, undated; 20 items (Box 69)
    Includes found art, Power's Poultry for Profit!.
  - Sketches, and titled - pen and ink, 1968; 1993; 1999; undated; 9 items (Box 69)
    Includes Literacy Through Photography certificate; Dare to be Different; Between Sentences; Affections to Leonardo + Bruegel + Orozco; Allegory of California; and To Allen.
  - Collages, mixed media, 2018; undated; 5 items (Box 69)
  - Watercolors, undated; 6 items (Box 69)
    Includes Proposed Postcard with Emphasis on the Attractions of Swimming.
  - Sketches - pen and ink, undated; 20 items (Box 69)
  - Sketches - brown ink, undated; 11 items (Box 69)
  - Sketches - pen and ink, undated; 13 items (Box 69)
- Others' Works, 1976-2018; undated
  This Series includes manuscripts, typescripts, and articles written by others, and arranged alphabetically by the author's last name.
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, 1976 (Box 70)
    Crusoe in England
  - Bonner, J.W., 2004 (Box 70)
    Allan Gurganus DLB
  - Bram, Christopher, undated (Box 70)
    Can Straight Men Still Write
  - Buford, Byron, 1988 (Box 70)
    And the Lord Knows What
  - Cerquone, Joe, 1992 (Box 70)
    Includes an article on Gurganus's Reassurance
  - Chaucer, Geoffrey, undated (Box 70)
    Chaucer's Retraction
  - Flowers, Linda, undated (Box 70)
    untitled
  - Giraldi, William, 2012 (Box 70)
    The Searing: On the Fiction of Allan Gurganus
  - Halloran, Amy, 1995 (Box 70)
    The Sky
  - Hillman, Brenda, undated (Box 70)
    Rhopalic Aubade
  - Holbert, Bruce, undated (Box 70)
    Hawk Creek Trilogy with included correspondence
  - Jones, Paul, undated (Box 70)
    The Coldest Night in Years
  - Lewis, Heather, 1995 (Box 70)
  - Marlette, Doug, 1991; 2001; 2 folders (Box 70)
    Marlette '91; and The Bridge, with included correspondence.
  - Meschery, Joanne, undated (Box 70)
    A Gentleman's Guide to the Frontier
  - Moose, Ruth, 1989 (Box 22)
    The Wreath Ribbon Quilt and Other Stories, with an inscription from Ruth Moose to Gurganus.
  - Own, Norton, undated (Box 70)
    A Certain Place: The Jacob's Pillow Story, includes inscription.
  - Rogers, Frank D., undated (Box 70)
    Confessions of an Undertaker 1900
  - Sanford, Mary Pettis, undated (Box 70)
    A Quiet Paradise
  - Seymour, Robert, 1991 (Box 22)
    Whites Only: A Pastor's Retrospective on Signs of the New South, with inscription to Gurganus.
  - Shapiro, Alan, undated (Box 70)
    Poetry
  - Simpson, Mona, 2000-2001; undated; 4 folders (Box 70)
    Includes Off Keck Road, with notes and correspondence from Gurganus; and Anywhere But Here party invitation.
  - Spencer, Elizabeth, undated; 3 folders (Box 70)
    The Boy in the Tree; Blackie, with Gurganus correspondence; and On the Hill.
  - Spiro, Ellen, undated (Box 70)
    Roam Sweet Home
  - Taylor, Paul, 2013 (Box 22)
    Facts and Fancies, with a note to Gurganus.
  - Welty, Eudora, 1998 (Box 70)
  - Vernon, Zackary, 2012 Dec (Box 70)
    Halloween's Herald of Democracy: Allan Gurganus and the Horror Show of American Politics
- Accession 2020-0100
  Access restricted: Acc. 2020-0100 requires additional arrangement, description, and/or screening. Contact Research Services for more information.
  The following description of the contents will need to be verified when the collection is processed: includes a scrapbook with photographs and clippings related to Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All, the 1974 issue of the New Yorker in which the story "Minor Heroism" was published (the first story that featured a gay character in the magazine), and approximately 15 letters to Gurganus from John Cheever from the 1970s.
  - Unprocessed files (Box 73, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76)